This video sponsored by the book summary
app, Blinkist. Discover, learn from, and
refresh yourself on the world's best
books. Use the link in the description
and you'll receive a free trial and 30%
off.
No Longer Human is arguably one of the
starkest and most accurate depictions of
loneliness, despair, [music]
social anxiety, and self-destruction
that has ever been written.
It puts you inside these states, evoking
a disturbing disquiet, not through
chaos, graphicness, [music] or violence,
but a kind of mundanity and an immense
heightened awareness of simple thought
and human activity.
In placing you so deeply inside the head
of a character, it almost becomes
difficult to see a clear humanity
anymore.
What becomes clear, however, is the
often immense distance between who we
are and how [music] we act in the world.
How we are compelled to both portray and
hide ourselves in a society whose
patience and tolerance is extremely
thin.
The book, originally titled Disqualified
as a Human Being, was written by
Japanese author Osamu Dazai. It was his
last novel, published in 1948, the same
year he died, making the title eerily
imbued with a second meaning.
Dazai is widely regarded as one of the
most influential and prominent [music]
Japanese authors in history, and No
Longer Human is considered a classic of
Japanese literature. The book's dark
themes and the main character's [music]
troubling experiences are only further
deepened and made more disturbing by the
fact that the work is
semi-autobiographical,
ultimately exploring a
semi-fictionalized version of the
confessions of Dazai himself.
Within the novel, through a series of
notebooks, we follow a young man named
Oba Yozo as he recounts different
periods of his life. The voice and
structure carrying a confessional
diary-like tone.
Immediately, it is revealed that Yozo
feels fundamentally different and
disconnected from humanity.
At an early age, he can't seem to
understand people. He finds what they do
and care about utterly boring, strange,
or terrifying.
There seems to be no functional bridge
between himself and others.
Fittingly, the first notebook begins
with Yozo not understanding what a
literal bridge is for and why humanity
would ever bother constructing one.
He writes,
>> [music]
>> "I climbed up and down the station
bridge, quite unaware that its function
was to permit people to cross from one
track to another. I was convinced that
the bridge had been provided to lend an
exotic touch and to make the station
premises a place of pleasant diversity,
like some foreign playground. I remained
under this delusion for quite a long
time and it was for me a very refined
amusement indeed to climb up and down
the bridge. I thought that it was one of
the most elegant services provided by
the railways.
When later I discovered that the bridge
was nothing more than a utilitarian
device,
I lost all interest in it."
Yozo's early detachment from a normal
orientation of the world is so severe,
he doesn't even understand the sensation
of hunger. He doesn't get why people
want to eat. Desire itself, in the most
literal sense, [music] is strange and
almost grotesque to him. Of course, he
consumes food, but the primary reason
for why he does
>> [music]
>> is devastating.
A representation of what is to come
throughout the rest of his life.
He eats in order to please others,
to act human.
He writes,
"Whenever I was asked what I wanted, my
first impulse was to answer, 'Nothing.'
The thought went through my mind that it
didn't make any difference, that nothing
was going to make me happy.
At the same time, I was congenitally
unable to refuse anything [music]
offered to me by another person, no
matter how little it might suit my
tastes.
When I hated something, I could not
pronounce the words,
>> [music]
>> 'I don't like it.'"
Throughout adolescence, Yozo goes to
extreme lengths to please others and
appear like a normal human. He creates
an entire persona in order to do so,
ultimately building a bridge between
himself and the world out of the remains
of his own self-sacrifice.
He assumes the persona of a jester,
always joking and acting with humor, not
because he enjoys humor, but because if
he can make people laugh, they will let
him in without ever having to know or
question [music] him.
It's a kind of Trojan horse into
humanity, only he never gets out of the
structure.
He perpetually hides inside,
>> [music]
>> he writes.
As a child, I had absolutely no notion
of what others, even members of my own
family, might be suffering or what they
were thinking. I was aware only of my
own unspeakable fears and
embarrassments.
Before anyone realized it, I had become
an accomplished clown, a child who never
spoke a single truthful word.
Yozo recognizes that humanity and
society [music] function on a kind of
exchange of mutual deceit.
And so, like eating, he participates out
of necessity for survival. [music]
But this only further takes him from
himself.
He writes,
"I'm convinced that human life is filled
with many pure, happy, serene examples
of insincerity, truly splendid of their
kind. Of people deceiving one another
without, strangely enough, any wounds
being inflicted. Of people who seem
unaware that they are deceiving one
another.
But I have no special interest in
instances of mutual deception.
I find it difficult to understand the
kind of human being who lives, or who is
sure he can live, purely, happily,
serenely, [music] while engaged in
deceit."
By adulthood, Yozo's [music] mask has
begun to calcify onto his face. He's no
longer just playing a character. He sort
of become stuck to one. [music] The
unique perspectives and interests he
experienced as a young boy, the joy and
kind of wisdom of seeing a world for
itself, comprised of objects from which
their amusements were derived from his
personal relationship with and
interpretations of them.
This all becomes diluted, then
dissolved. [music]
This loss inflames a depression and
anxiety.
The world, [music] including himself,
has receded into impossibility.
Soon, all Yozo's interactions, any
praise he receives, any alleviations of
guilt, any flaws or faults, his
relationships, and so on, become
filtered through a false self.
There's almost no person left to feel,
to possess any ownership over experience
or achievement, fault or flaw.
Though glimmers of a self still
occasionally show in brief moments of
artistic engagement, intoxication, or
love, they are short-lived and quickly
recede into the blackness of the
unconscious.
Ultimately, what Yozhik fears about
life, about being rejected and never
understood, about humanity being a
strange and dreadful species,
>> [music]
>> becomes a kind of self-fulfilling
prophecy. In fearing rejection, he
constantly modifies himself to fit the
world. In constantly modifying and
hiding himself, he ultimately rejects
himself, never allowing himself out or
the world in.
In fearing being known, he becomes
unknowable.
>> [music]
>> In needing to be accepted, he becomes no
one.
What is left is a kind of spiraling of
self-denial and self-destruction,
[music]
where all motion in his life is fueled
by the combustion of psychological
debris.
Alienation and self-destruction spread
out from the inside, finding their way
into his hands as they grab at bottles
of alcohol and drugs.
Yozhik's world becomes reflective of his
unaddressed inner turmoil. The pressure
and effort of maintaining a functional
self that isn't made of anything he
understands or cares about becomes so
heavy, the surface begins to crack,
revealing not a truer self, but a
nebulous chaos.
In the end, [music] he's removed from
society and placed in a mental
institution.
From one madhouse to [music] another.
It is a reasonable interpretation to see
this story as a call to authenticity.
>> [music]
>> In many ways, that is a sound
interpretation and a useful lesson to
pull from it. We must be and express
ourselves [music]
in every moment in which it's
appropriate, and we must strive to
confront and understand ourselves as
honestly [music] as we can.
We must live with a kind of courage to
be rejected, to be misunderstood, to be
disliked. Otherwise, we risk losing our
sense of self completely.
We risk never really being known by
anyone at all.
And we risk losing control and
orientation in [music] life, drifting
into patterns of aimlessness or
destruction.
"Your worst sin," wrote Fyodor
Dostoevsky in Crime and Punishment, is
that you have destroyed and betrayed
yourself for nothing.
But it's more complicated than that.
And the truth is more devastating.
Firstly, it isn't obvious how much
forthrightness is appropriate across
various moments and context of life and
society. Yozo isn't wrong to notice that
there's a kind of functional positive
deceit [music]
intrinsic to human interactions. And he
isn't wrong to form and operate through
a functional persona in the world.
>> [music]
>> We all do this, at least on some level.
We present a self to the world that
differs from our so-called authentic
self. And we present different selves in
different contexts.
>> [music]
>> And the balance of authenticity versus
pretense isn't always obvious.
We are prone to miss the mark often and
meaningfully, especially if we find
ourselves sharing anything like the
perspective, awareness, or personal
divergence [music]
of Yozo.
Yozo's problem isn't that he's wrong
about how the world is. It's that,
[music]
in many ways, he's right. And the gap
between his assessments of the world and
his [music] true self seems, at least to
him, unbridgeable. And he's hyper aware
of this gap, of himself and his relation
to an absurd world. His problem is found
in that he wants to bridge this gap, but
can't. At least not authentically and
functionally. It's one or the other,
or perhaps neither.
If we return to the opening of the first
notebook, Yozo was a young boy confused
about a world and a self he had no say
[music] in.
"Mine has been a life of much shame." He
writes as the opening line.
This shame indicates a desire to be
right, to fit in, to be good, to be
normal.
But he can't.
That is the shame and the tragedy.
He can't be himself and be functional in
society. For whatever reason, he is the
way he is. And so, what is he supposed
to do?
>> [music]
>> Be himself in a world that will
ostracize him? Enjoy his self-alienation
productively and happily?
At the end of the novel, in the
epilogue, [music]
the perspective shifts. It is no longer
Yozo's narration. It is the perspective
of an individual who appears to be some
sort of writer who's come into
possession of Yozo's notebooks.
He's obtained them from a barkeeper of a
bar Yozo had previously frequented.
After reading the notebooks, the
individual asks the barkeeper about her
reaction when she read them.
>> [music]
>> "Did you cry?"
She responds,
"No, I didn't cry.
I just kept thinking that when human
beings get that [music] way,
they're no good for anything."
This is perhaps the most tragic part.
Yozo was caught in a loop that he never
had a real chance of escaping from. And
in the end, society doesn't really care
or offer him any help. Society doesn't
tend to those who struggle to
understand, engage with, or produce
value for it.
Even close friends and family members of
individuals can and often do receive
their love and attention from those who
no longer meet a baseline measure of
functionality or productive value. Even
if, and sometimes especially if, the
individual is hamstrung with depression,
anxiety, or addiction.
The Yozos of the world are often left
alone in their head with an unstable
bridge with little to no footprints on
its surface.
As previously mentioned, the book is
widely regarded as a
semi-autobiographical recounting of
Dazai's actual life and experience.
This makes it all the more devastating,
but in a way, it also makes it all the
more beautiful. Dazai struggled
throughout his life to understand and be
understood by humanity.
But through his [music] work, he
ultimately built his bridge.
One that is not only sturdy, but
profound, and ironically,
>> [music]
>> useful.
A unique and beautifully constructed
bridge that offers transport into a
realm of the human psyche
>> [music]
>> so many of us experience firsthand, but
have very rarely been invited in to see
or discuss [music] it plainly with
others.
Through art and literature, Dazai found
a way out of his head and into the
world. [music]
And he found a way to let the world in.
If only he hadn't exited life when he
did, perhaps he could have seen more
plainly how much his own experience was
shared,
how much his work helped others,
and how much the world [music] truly
knew him.
As put in the introduction of a
translation of the book by Donald Keene,
No longer human is not a cheerful
[music] book, yet its effect is far from
that of a painful wound gratuitously
inflicted on the reader.
>> [music]
>> As a reviewer wrote to Dazai's earlier
novel,
such is the power of art to transfigure
what is objectively ignoble or depraved
that is actually [music] deeply moving
and even inspiriting.
To know the nature of despair and to
triumph over it in the ways that are
possible to oneself,
imagination was Dazai's only weapon
>> [music]
>> and surely a sort of grace.
In the end, Dazai offers something
ironically far more human than we are
used to, an [music] honest communion
with the absurdity of our relationship
with ourselves and the world, a
relationship that is often
insurmountable or tragic, but
nonetheless deeply [music] common and
real.
The book ends with the barkeeper saying,
>> [music]
>> "It's his father's fault. The Yozo we
knew was so easygoing and amusing. And
if only he hadn't [music] drunk. No,
even though he did drink, he was a good
boy,
an angel."
Here we see that Yozo wasn't even
perceived as being particularly weird or
negative by the people who knew him.
In this final blow, Dazai seems to want
to show us that the most tormented among
us, those who feel a strangeness of
being with immense intensity, [music]
can and often do go their whole lives
without this suffering ever being known,
without it ever being properly
understood,
without them ever being understood.
>> [music]
>> Your father, your partner, your closest
friend,
you.
How similar [music] and in what ways are
we to Yozo?
So much of who we are is hidden to the
world and to ourselves.
We have done so much to fit in, to be
liked,
to be human.
For many of us, it isn't clear what is
left.
But it is up to each of us to find out
what is
and to share it
while we still can.
Some of the most important books we
could ever read in life are books we
might not ever discover. And some of the
best books we'll ever read are books
we've already read. The key is not
merely to read more books, but to read
better books, and to engage in the ones
we love more effectively. With the near
infinite number of options and streams
of content we are always bombarded with,
it could be extremely difficult and
time-consuming [music] to do this
successfully.
However, with this video sponsor,
Blinkist, you can easily and effectively
return to the books that you love, that
have already changed your life, and
discover all sorts of new books that
will help further shape you. With over
9,000 titles across wide-ranging topics,
Blinkist beautifully curates and breaks
down books into around 15-minute
summaries and key takeaways, which can
be both read and listened to even while
offline. Whether you want to refresh
yourself on classics [music] like Crime
and Punishment by Fyodor Dostoevsky, or
learn about the life and work of
psychiatrist Viktor Frankl, exploring
how humans can endure the seemingly
unendurable while creating meaning in a
seemingly meaningless world in Frankl's
book, Man's Search for Meaning. Blinkist
makes it easy and enjoyable to become a
lifelong learner who is always
increasing and refining their mental
toolbox, so you can [music] approach
ideas, decisions, and life in general
with more clarity.
And for titles you discover that you
love, the complete book is always there
to go deeper. Whether you're on a walk,
a commute, [music] in line, or sitting
quietly with yourself, Blinkist helps
you find wonder and knowledge in every
moment. Get a free trial and save an
additional 30% [music] off by going to
blinkist.com/wonder
or clicking the link in the description.
Blinkist has been a long-time partner of
the channel, and I can't recommend them
enough. And of course,
>> [music]
>> as always, thank you so much for
watching in general, and see you next
video.